so right can you give a couple of
examples the sort of practical
implementation of mushroom technologies
that could help with bioremediation and
also with food security of growing fungi
create soils this simplest way of
describing is fungi break down rocks and
rocks become more fragile and they
crumble and they have cavities that hold
water and so the my silly ation of
habitats retains water in the habitats
with retaining water you benefit plants
so my ciliated habitats tend to be water
more to be water retentive less erosion
and support biological communities that
they thrive with that an environment so
fungi predetermined downstream many of
the biological communities that live
upon to mycelial mats are growing
underneath the ground practical
solutions would include unfortunately
all habitats are becoming increasingly
more contaminated so with people wonder
when they buy a new tire they drive down
the road and fifty thousand miles later
they have to buy a new tire where did
the hydrocarbons go they went on the
road now they're washing into the
streams and impugning you know that
ecosystems of the fisheries you know and
aquatic animals and birds legions of
other organisms so with these funds I do
so well as they break down plant tissue
especially lignin cellulose produced
some enzymes lignin TSA's and cellulases
these are a little Pacman like enzymes
that go around and they dismantle large
molecular complexes and simpler forms
well by a wonderful quirk of nature the
same enzymes break down oil and so
breaking down hydrocarbons with enzymes
with fungi is one way of decontaminating
and habitat and one test of habitat
toxicity is called the warm toxicity
test and you put a hundred worms into a
vessel with soil if it's toxic it really
toxic all the worms die and our
experiments we do mycelium onto that
toxic soil and it breaks down the toxins
you put the hundred worms into the into
the soil that is forming toxic and they
live and reproduce that is a biological
test of toxicity because invertebrates
are especially sensitive the hydrocarbon
contamination there's dozens of examples
like that and you can use the mycelium
as filtration media to prevent coliform
bacteria and toxic waste from flowing
the downstream downs
environments and so the membranes of
mycelium our digestive membranes they're
really externalized stomachs and we
share a more common evolutionary history
with fungi than we do with any other
kingdom splitting off from funds about
650 million years ago fungi went their
route of externally digesting its
nutrients we went the route of
encapsulating on nutrients within the
cellular sack producing digestive
enzymes within and that was there was
basically one of the major splits
between fungi and animals and and so
using these fungal membranes the
wonderful thing about them that they
have plasticity of use they're extremely
resilient adaptive and they have
trillions upon trillions of in
branchings and the work of Patrick
Hickey in particular has shown that
these mycelial membranes are are
advancing bundles of nuclei that are
constant migration throughout the
network and if there's a new genetic
expression that produces a new enzyme
that's targeted again and successful
against a new toxin what will happen
well before that enzyme was produced the
mycelium would advance in that toxin
after the enzyme is produced the
mycelium de facto grows in that toxin
that then information that that Network
has gained is genetically encoded into
the network and so these membranes learn
then they can learn very quickly and so
these things are like extents you know
mycelial interphase computers that are
constantly sorting and figuring out
different strategies of overcoming
obstacles and we face a lot of obstacles
but these things are a lot smarter than
we are and I think engaging my cell
networks for advancing you know growing
food and toxic habitats preventing
content downstream contamination
bolstering biodiversity by creating the
soil matrix that gives spring to life
forms all of these are part of the
within the tool set of the skill base
that these my cellular networks have
resident within them